Finding Aid for Men's Glee Club (University of Michigan) records 1886-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Men's Glee Club (University of Michigan) Records
1886-2012
University of Michigan. Men's Glee Club.
87250 BImu Bimu F19 2
University of Michigan choral group founded in 1859; includes correspondence, administrative records, musical scores, publicity material, photographs, posters and sound recordings in addition to digitized versions of records and born digital audio, video, and still images
16.5 linear feet
7 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
460.1 GB
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Records have been received in periodic accessions since 1960. Included in the collection are records received in Dec. 1985 (donor # 3624 ), and records received from Philip Duey in Dec. 1979 (donor # 6409 ). Additional recordings and material from the 2012 trip to China were received in 2012.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open for research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
As early as 1846 University of Michigan students met regularly to sing "for pure enjoyment." In 1859 the university formally acknowledged this activity through the establishment of a Glee Club. Michigan's group was the second such college organization formed in the nation.
In its early days the club included from seven to twelve singers who performed college songs, humorous vaudeville numbers and skits. In the 1870s the larger group began to divide into smaller performing units, trios and quartets, which allowed for greater individual recognition. In the 1880s the club began to tour and in 1884 the organization made its first excursion outside of the state. Because of the demands of touring the size of the club was expanded, first to sixteen members, four men per part, and by the turn of the century to around fifty members.
After World War I the club experienced difficult times. A lack of sound musical programs led to declining audiences, and in 1920 a disastrous West Coast tour lost so much money that the club was unable to tour for five years. In 1921, as part of an effort to revive itself, the club became part of the Michigan Union. In 1922 the name "Men's Glee Club" was formally adopted and the club experimented with new music. An all classical format was first adopted, and when this proved unsuccessful it was changed to the balanced program of classical, humorous and college songs still used today. The club also began to formally participate in the annual Michigan Union Operas, an all male comedy review.
All of these changes led to a revival in the club's fortunes. Touring was resumed, which eventually caused the club to withdraw from the Union Operas, because the two groups' separate touring schedules made it impossible for members to participate in both. In 1943 the club formally ended its affiliation with the Union and resumed its prior status, as an independent student organization.
After World War II the club evolved new traditions and expanded its touring activity. In 1952 the club began the Fall custom of singing with the Glee Club of a school that had played the University of Michigan that day in a football game. In 1955 the popular double quartet, the Friars, was first organized. 1955 also marked the club's first European tour, which was followed by international tours in 1959, 1963, 1967, 1971, 1978, 1989, and 1992. The tours of 1959 and 1963 were highlighted by victories at the International Musical Eisteddfod in Llangollen, Wales. 2012 saw the club embark on a successful tour of the People's Republic of China.
When the club was first organized, and for many years thereafter, musical directorship was entrusted to a club member. In the 1870s and 1880s, however, the club began to experiment with hiring a professional director, usually a music teacher from the Ann Arbor area. In 1894 the club returned to appointing one of their own members as director, but the idea of hiring a professional remained and in 1908 the club resumed the practice of hiring a director.
Professional Director's of the Men's Glee Club
1885-1889 Ross G. Cole
1890-1892 Albert A. Stanley
1892-1893 Silas R. Mills
1908-1911 Earle Killeen
1911-1914 William A. Howland
1914-1919 Theodore Harrison
1919-1920 Russell Carter
1920-1922 Frank L. Thomas
1922-1924 George O. Bowen
1924-1930 Theodore Harrison
1930-1931 Arthur Hackett
1931-1947 David E. Mattern
1947-1955 Philip A. Duey
1955-1956 Walter S. Collins (acting)
1956-1969 Philip A. Duey
1969-1975 Willis C. Patterson
1975-1981 Leonard Johnson
1981-1987 Patrick Gardner
1987-1988 Bradley Bloom
1988-2002 Jerry Blackstone
2002-2005 Stephen Lusmann
2005-2011 Paul Rardin
2012- Eugene Rogers
The records of the Men's Glee Club date from 1886 to 2012 and were received in several major accessions. The first accession, covering 1886-1985 and 1991, includes four linear feet of manuscript, printed, and photographic material as well as posters, scrapbooks, and sound recordings in a variety of formats. The first accession has been divided into five series: Chronological File, Philip A. Duey Material, Photographs, Sound Recordings, Scrapbooks, and Archived Website.
The 1995 accession of the records of the Men's Glee Club were comprised of two linear feet of correspondence, photographs, and topical files ranging from 1919 to 1994. Items of particular interest include a folder of historical writings, which provides anecdotes, reflections, and facts about the club prepared for an exhibit on club history. The Press Releases folder is also of note, as it reflects information given out by the club to newspapers and other media of the towns they visited. Both of these folders are found in the Topical series. The records of this accession are divided into 3 series: Correspondence, Topical, and Visual Materials.
The 2010 accession to the University of Michigan Men's Glee Club records is organized into one series. The Sound Recordings series, 1952-1987, (10 linear feet) is comprised of University of Michigan Men's Glee Club concert recordings, including its annual fall and spring concert series. Many of the boxes of tape reel also include a concert program and concert set list.
The 2012 accession consisted entirely of digital materials (scanned images, audio files, video files, and still images) that added content to the Chronological Files series and established a China Concert Tour series.
Subjects:
Friars (Musical group); Michigan Union Opera.; University of Michigan--Choral organizations.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan. Men's Glee Club.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Choral singing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material
Duey, Philip A., d. 1982.; Friars (Musical group); Mandolin Club (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Men's Glee Club.; University of Michigan--Choral organizations.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
Contributors:
Duey, Philip A., d. 1982.
Genre/Form:
Scrapbooks.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Chronological File
  (BHL deposit ID: 87250_0002)
  The Chronological File represents the basic records of the collection. Arranged by academic year, it consists primarily of printed concert programs, newspaper clippings and other publicity material, occasional financial records (generally summary statements of club finances for an academic year), details regarding tours (particularly the annual spring tour), and minutes. Many posters were included in the Chronological File. Unfolded posters have been housed separately in an oversized folder. This series contains four individual documents of particular note. A fifteen page club history written by John Payne is found in 1958-1959. Narrative logs of the club's international trips in 1955, 1959 and 1967 were maintained and are filed in the appropriate years. Chronological File materials from 1886-1969 have been scanned and these digital versions may be found in the Bentley Library's digital repository.
  The 2012 additions to the Chronological Files series include digitized images of content in the first two boxes of the series, spanning the years 1886-1969. Glee Club members scanned this content as part of an organizational project in 2011. Digital versions of Laudes, the official newsletter of the Men's Glee Club, were also part of the addition. These newsletters were published biannually and span the years 2000-2011 (with the Fall 2009 issue missing from the accession). Both the original and digital copies have been retained.[BHL deposit ID: 87250_0002]
  - 1886-1893 (Box 1)
  - 1911/121-1941/42, 28 folders (Box 1)
  - 1944/45-1956/957, 18 folders (Box 1)
  - 1957/58-1968/69, 21 folders (Box 2)
  - 1969/70-1984/85, 17 folders (Box 3)
  - Undated
    - General (Box 3)
    - Songs (Box 3)
    - Plays, Skits and Stories (Box 3)
    - Programs (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings and Other Publicity (Box 3)
  - "Laudes" (official newsletter), 2000-2011
- Philip A. Duey
  The Philip A. Duey Material consists of only two folders, one detailing the radio career of the Club's one time director before he came to Ann Arbor and the other containing miscellaneous personal material. A few newspaper clippings about Duey before he came to the University of Michigan are found in the appropriate chronological folder, particularly 1946-1947.
  - Radio Career (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Photographs and Posters (see also boxes 5, 6 and 8)
  The Photographs (some oversize) consist primarily of group pictures, tour pictures, photos of the Novelaires and the Friars, Philip Duey photographs, and a few Union Opera pictures. A few photographs are also located in the Chronological File.
  - Group Photos
    - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - With Pat Boone and Dinah Shore (Box 3)
    - Novelaires and Friars (Box 3)
    - Rehearsals (Box 3)
  - Individuals
    - General (Box 3)
    - Philip A. Duey (Box 3)
  - Tours
    - General (Box 3)
    - 1896, 1959, 1963, 1971 (negatives only), 1978 (8 envelopes), 1896-1978 (Box 3)
- Photographs and Posters
  - Photos (Box 5)
  - Photos (Box 6)
    (continued)
- Correspondence
  Arranged chronologically by season, the Correspondence series mostly reflects the negotiations the club's business manager conducted to secure appearances for the club. The bulk of the letters come from the early 1920s, with two additional folders from the late 1930s. The "1923 West Coast Trip" folder gives the most accurate representation of the often arduous process taken to secure dates and venues for tours. Of note is a letter of thanks from President Gerald R. Ford
  - 1919-1920 (Box 7)
  - 1922-1923 (Box 7)
  - 1923 (Box 7)
    (West Coast Trip)
  - 1923-1924 (Box 7)
  - 1937-1938 (Box 7)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 7)
  - Gerald R. Ford, 1975 (Box 7)
- Topical
  The Topical file deals largely with items documenting the tours upon which the Men's Glee Club frequently embarked. The performance contracts, though not complete, provide a useful and extensive overview of the types of places, venues, and dates the club played and the terms and conditions they demanded. The "Constitution and By-Laws" folder gives an overview of Glee Club policies and administrative operations. The folders in the "Tours" subseries are comprised of materials the club put together in preparation for travel and include itineraries and guides to their destinations.
  - Account Book, 1938-1939 (Box 7)
  - Account Book, 1979-1984 (Box 7)
  - City and County of Denver Proclamation, 2010 (Box 7)
  - Constitution and By-laws (Box 7)
  - Contracts
    - 1922-1926 (Box 7)
    - 1947-1954 (Box 7)
    - 1955-1958 (Box 7)
    - 1959-1961 (Box 7)
    - 1962-1977 (Box 7)
    - 1987-1993 (Box 7)
  - Count Basie Concert, 1957 (Box 7)
  - Historical Writings (Box 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 7)
  - Novelaires, 1950 (Box 7)
  - Press Releases (Box 7)
  - Tours
    - China, 2012 (Box 7)
    - Eastern and Central Europe, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Llangollen International Musical Eisteddfod, undated (Box 7)
    - Midwest, 1994 (Box 7)
    - Orient, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Schedules, 1948-1959 (Box 7)
    - Schedules, 1985-1993 (Box 7)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series gives a view of club activities from several different eras. "Group Portraits" show the Glee Club posing for photos and contains photos of the club singing or performing other activities. The "Publicity Shots" provide an interesting window to the era when the Glee Club participated in the all-male Michigan Union Operas. The record group also holds an extensive number of color snapshots with negatives of the club's 1987 tour. An oversized folder of publicity posters forms another section of visual materials. Two photo albums and a film of the club's 1964 appearance on the Perry Como television show round out the series.
  - Photographs
    - Conductors (Box 8)
    - Friars (Box 8)
    - Group Portraits, Dated (Box 8)
    - Group Portraits, Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Groups, Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Individuals (Box 8)
    - Officers (Box 8)
    - Performance, 1986 (Box 8)
    - Publicity Shots (Box 8)
    - Reunion (Box 8)
    - Soloists (Box 8)
    - Tour (Upper Peninsula), 1936 (Box 8)
    - Tour, 1987; 9 envelopes (Box 8)
    - Tour (China), 1989 (Box 8)
  - Photo Albums
    - European Tour, 1985 (Box 8)
    - East Coast Tour, 1988 (Box 8)
  - Film (16mm)
    - Appearance on the Perry Como Show, 1964 (Box 8)
- Scrapbooks (BImu/F19)
  The Scrapbooks are arranged chronologically and primarily contain newspaper clippings and programs.
  - [1], 1923 (Box 8)
  - [2], 1938 (Box 8)
  - European Tour [Special Location: B283/3], 1955 (Box 8)
  - [3], 1960-1961 (Box 8)
  - [4], 1964 (Box 8)
  - World Tour [5], 1966-1967 (Box 8)
  - [6], 1967-1968 (Box 8)
- Sound Recordings
  - Phonograph records, Cassettes, CDs
    - Centennial Spring Concert, 1959; Phonograph Record, 33 1/3 rpm (Box4 4)
      - [Side 1], [87250-SR-100-1-1]; mp3 file; (Men's Glee Club 1959 Centennial Concert with Director Philip A. Duey. Original recording made by WUOM. Laudes Atque Carmina; Invocation of Orpheus; Come My Beloved; To The Women; Is My Team Plowing; Stomp Your Foot; Go Lovely Rose; Balm in Gilead; Die MusikantenSide 2Band 1 Medley: To The Women; Band 2 Shadrach; Band 3 Ding Dong Daddy; I'll Nee'r Forget My College Days; Band 4 Michigan Men; Drink, Drink, Joy Rules the Day; Band 5 Hymn from "Voices of Michigan"; Band 6 The Old Friars Song; The Victors; The Yellow and the Blue.)
      - [Side 2], [87250-SR-100-1-2]; mp3 file; (Men's Glee Club 1959 Centennial Concert with Director Philip A. Duey. Original recording made by WUOM. Laudes Atque Carmina; Invocation of Orpheus; Come My Beloved; To The Women; Is My Team Plowing; Stomp Your Foot; Go Lovely Rose; Balm in Gilead; Die MusikantenSide 2Band 1 Medley: To The Women; Band 2 Shadrach; Band 3 Ding Dong Daddy; I'll Nee'r Forget My College Days; Band 4 Michigan Men; Drink, Drink, Joy Rules the Day; Band 5 Hymn from "Voices of Michigan"; Band 6 The Old Friars Song; The Victors; The Yellow and the Blue.)
    - "Michigan Songs", circa 1978; 1 audiocassette (Box 4)
    - 1988-89 (live recordings), 1 compact disc (Box 4)
  - Reel-to-Reel Tapes
    [Digitized audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.]
    The Sound Recordings series, Reel-to-reel 1952-1987, (10 linear feet) is comprised of University of Michigan Men's Glee Club concert recordings, including its annual fall and spring concert series. Many of the boxes of tape reel also include a concert program and concert set list.
    - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club, 1953 November 06; 3 audiotapes Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 15 ips (Box4 4)
      - [Part 1], [87250-SR-1-1-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 1; The University of Michigan Men's Glee Club performing: (Section 1) Eyes, Wondrous Eyes; Music Will Calm Thee; Lord Randall; Casey Jones; (Section 2) The Heart Worships; Night and Dreams; Hallelujah, Amen; Clementine; Invocation from Orpheus; Good Fellows be Merry. Two unlabeled tapes not digitized)
    - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club at Ryukyu Islands, Japan, 1967 June 01; 4 Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips (Box4 4)
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [87250-SR-2-1-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 1; Glee Club Concert at Ryukyu Islands Concert Hall performing Laudes; Dona; Ave Verum; Echo Song; Hi Ho; Alleluia Amen.)
      - [Tape 2, Part 1], [87250-SR-2-2-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 2; Glee Club Concert at Ryukyu Islands Concert Hall performing Piano Selections (2); Ave Maria; Japanese Song; Rose; For the People; Captain Hook; Stomp Your Foot.)
      - [Tape 3, Part 1], [87250-SR-2-3-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 3; Glee Club Concert at Ryukyu Islands Concert Hall performing Medley (Friars Octet)Very Special Girl; Mr. Bass Man; I Get Around.)
      - [Tape 4, Part 1], [87250-SR-2-4-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 4; Glee Club Concert at Ryukyu Islands Concert Hall performing Spirit in Thy Heart; Balm in Gilead; Jerusalem; Ain't Got Time to Die; Old Friars Song; Men of Michigan; Varsity; Victors; Yellow and Blue; Encore with Girl from Ipanema; Pollution)
    - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Recordings from 1952-1987, 1952 May 10; 3 Audio Reel-to-Reel, 10.5 inch, 15 ips (Box 9)
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [87250-SR-3-1-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 1 of 3; Concert Recordings of the University of Michigan Men's Glee Club 1952-1987 performing Laudes Atque Carmina; Invocation of Orpheus; Night and Dreams; Good Fellows Be Merry; Garden in the Rain; Darktown Strutters; We Three; Sing Maiden Sing; The Heart Worships; The Pirate Song; Shadrack; Casey Jones; What Was the Matter With Rachmaninoff?)
      - [Tape 2, Part 1], [87250-SR-3-2-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 2 of 3; University of Michigan Men's Glee Club performing Lord Randall; Gabriel; County Fair; Great Day; Sheik of Araby; Ballin' the Jack; Rural Rhythm.)
      - [Tape 3, Part 1], [87250-SR-3-3-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 3 of 3; University of Michigan Men's Glee Club performing: Tis of Michigan We Sing; A Toast to Michigan; I Want to Go Back to Michigan; I'll Never Forget My College Days (The Novelaires); Michigan Men; Goddess of the Inland Seas; The Yellow and Blue; Drink, Drink, Joy Rules the Day (Featuring Ara Berberian, Bass); Varsity; When Night Falls(Featuring Robert McGrath, Tenor); The Bum Army; The Old Friars' Song; The Victors.)
    - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club, 1952 May 25; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 10.5 inch, 15 ips (Box 9)
      - [Part 1], [87250-SR-4-1-1]; mp3 file; (University of Michigan Men's Glee Club concert. Songs unlisted.)
    - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club "Studio Showcase Philip A. Duey", 1952 July 25; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 10.5 inch, 15 ips (Box 9)
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [87250-SR-5-1-1]; mp3 file; (University of Michigan Men's Glee Club performs Handel: Nase al Bosco from "Ezio", Where'er you Walk from "Semele", O Ruddier than the Cherry from "Acis and Galatea", Thy Glorious Deeds from "Samson", Honor and Arms. Piano accompaniment by Wilber Perry.)
    - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & Cornell University Glee Club, 1952 November 07; 3 Audio Reel-to-Reel, 10.5 inch, 15 ips (Box 9)
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [87250-SR-6-1-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 1 of 3; The Cornell Glee Club performs: Strike Up a Song (Songs of Cornell); Cornell (Songs of Cornel, With Edwin Gibson, '53); My Heart is Victorious (Giacomo Carissimi); More Was Lost at Mohacs Field (F. Korbay); Finiculi, Finicula (Luigi Denza); Set Down Servant (Set Down Servant); La Danza (Rossini).)
      - [Tape 2, Part 1], [87250-SR-6-2-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 2 of 3; The Cornell Glee Club and Cayuga's Waiters performs Down in the Valley [text illegible]; Russian Picnic (arr. Harvey Enders); Early One Morning (arr. Gwynn Bement); Old Mother Hubbard (Victor Hely-Hutchinson). The University of Michigan Men's Glee Club performs Laudes Atque Carmina (Traditional Opening Hymn, A. A. Stanley); Music Will Calm Thee (From Rodelinda, Soloist-Robert Elson - Baritone, Handel); Hallelujah, Amen (from Judas Maccabeus, Handel).)
      - [Tape 3, Part 1], [87250-SR-6-3-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 3 of 3; The University of Michigan Men Glee Club and the Novelaires performs Woman in the Shoe; Eileen (Featuring Robert McGrath, Irish Folk Song); Shadrack (Featuring Russell Christopher, Baritone, Robert MacGimsey); Clementine (American Folk Song); County Fair (Featuring David Calahan, Tenor, and the Novelaires, Mel Torme); "Songs of Michigan" Tis of Michigan We Sing; A Toast to Michigan; I Want to Go Back To Michigan; The Old Friars Song; The Victors; Alma Maters by Combined Glee Clubs.)
    - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club Annual Spring Concert, 1953 May 16; 3 Audio Reel-to-Reel, 10.5 inch, 15 ips (Box 9)
      - [Tape 1, Part 1], [87250-SR-7-1-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 1 of 2; The University of Michigan Men's Glee Club performs Laudes Atque Carmina (Traditional Opening Hymn, A.A. Stanley); *Music Will Calm Thee (From Rodelinda, Handel (1685-1759), Soloist - George Hellwarth, baritone); *Wondrous Eyes (Caccini (1550(?)-1618); Echo Song (Lasso (1530-1594); *Hallelujah Amen (from Judas Maccabeus, Handel (1685-1759); A Sailor Loved a Lass (Storace); Largo al Factotum ((from "Barber of Seville") Featuring Russell Christopher, baritone Rossini); Song of Joy (A.T. Gretchaninoff); Northern Lights (Selim Palmgren); *Eileen (Featuring Robert McGreath, tenor, Irish Folk Song).)
      - [Tape 2, Part 1], [87250-SR-7-2-1]; mp3 file; (Tape 2 of 2; University of Michigan Men's Glee Club performs Shadrack, County Fair, Woman in the Shoe, Clementine; Gershwin Medley (Clap-a yo' Hands, Somebody Loves Me, Nobody But You, S'Wonderful, Who Cares, Soon). Additional selections by the Novelaires Quartette: Do I worry; Dearie; We Three; Floatin' Down to Cottontown.)
      - [Part 1], [87250-SR-8-1-1]; mp3 file; (The Ohio State Glee Club performs: Oh, Rejoice, Ye Christians Loudly; Ave Maria; And Now tis Time to Go; Selections by the OSUGLEECQS: Ol' Joe Clark, Tee Roo, There Is Nothin' Like A Dame, Campus Echoes, Wahoo, It's round on the end, I wanna go back, etc. Michigan Glee Club performs: Laudes Atque Carmina, A Mighty Fortress Is Our God, Care Selve, The Omnipotence. Selections by "The Novelaires" In The Silence of the Night, Nola, Luck Be A Lady, Songs of Michigan Tis of Michigan We Sing, A Toast to Michigan, I Want To Go Back To Michigan, Victors, The Old Friar's Song. Show concludes with Alma Maters by combined Glee Clubs.)
    - University of Michigan Men's Glee Club & Ohio State University Glee Club Joint Concert, 1953 November 21; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 10.5 inch, 7 1/2 ips
      - [Part 1], [87250-SR-8-1-1]; mp3 file; (The Ohio State Glee Club performs: Oh, Rejoice, Ye Christians Loudly; Ave Maria; And Now tis Time to Go; Selections by the OSUGLEECQS: Ol' Joe Clark, Tee Roo, There Is Nothin' Like A Dame, Campus Echoes, Wahoo, It's round on the end, I wanna go back, etc. Michigan Glee Club performs: Laudes Atque Carmina, A Mighty Fortress Is Our God, Care Selve, The Omnipotence. Selections by "The Novelaires" In The Silence of the Night, Nola, Luck Be A Lady, Songs of Michigan Tis of Michigan We Sing, A Toast to Michigan, I Want To Go Back To Michigan, Victors, The Old Friar's Song. Show concludes with Alma Maters by combined Glee Clubs.)